

# Nicolas Gensollen

- nicolas.gensollen@gmail.com
- 06.12.95.21.69
- 1 Rue Honoré d'Estienne d'Orves, 91120 Palaiseau
- https://nicolasgensollen.github.io
- https://github.com/NicolasGensollen
- https://twitter.com/Gensollen\_N

# **INTERESTS**

I am a computer scientist with a strong interest in software development and open source.

My main research interests are related to complex systems, machine learning, and networks. Since November 2020, I am a member of the PARIETAL team at INRIA Saclay, working on machine learning

softwares for neuroimaging. More information available on my website.

### **EXPERIENCE**

### **INRIA**, Research Engineer

Nov 2020 - Now

Inría\_

Engineer in the PARIETAL team, at INRIA, Saclay. Working on developping and maintaining neuroscience and machine learning softwares.



#### **LIP6**, Postdoc Researcher

Dec 2018 - Oct 2020

Postdoc in the Complex Networks team, at LIP6, Sorbonne University. Working on anomaly detection in large streams of interactions using a link stream based approach.

#### **NREL**. Postdoc Researcher

Mar 2017 - Nov 2018

Postdoc in the Power System Design and Studies group at NREL, working on stochastic optimization methods for power system engineering.

### **CONSEIL GENERAL 77**, Intern

Jul 2011 - Jan 2012



Intern working on the development of a scenario-pricing tool for Optical fiber deployment in the French Seine-et-Marne region.

### **EDUCATION**

#### PHD. COMPUTER SCIENCE

Oct 2013 - Oct 2016



PhD fellowship awarded by Telecom SudParis.

Telecommunications Networks and Services Department, Mines-Telecom Institute, CEA Saclay Nano-Innov.

Advised by: Vincent Gauthier, Michel Marot, and Monique Becker.

Thesis: Modeling and Optimizing a Distributed Power Network: A Complex System Approach of the Prosumer Management in the Smart Grid

Defense date: 7th October 2016

# **ENGINEER DEGREE - TELECOMMUNCATION**

Sep 2009 - Sep 2012



Telecom SudParis

Telecommunication engineer student, Telecom SudParis, Evry, France.

Last year option: Networking.

Advised by Laurent Bernard and Eric Gangloff.

*Languages:* Native Speaker

Native Speake Professional

Conversational level

Soft skills:

Problem-solving, creativity, and accountability

Time managment, open-mindedness, and adaptability

Communication, teamwork spirit, patience, and humility

Technical skills and incomplete list of related favorite tools:

Scientific programming and scripting: Python, Julia, Bash, Matlab

Web development: HTML, CSS, PHP, JavaScript

Other programming languages: C, C++, C#, Visual Basics

**VCS, CI, CD:** Git, GitHub, GitLab, Jenkins

Writing and Documentation: LaTeX, Markdown, Sphinx, Documenter.jl

Machine Learning: Scikit-learn, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Flux.jl, statsmodels

Optimization and scientific programming: NumPy, Scipy, Pandas, JuMP

Visualization: Matplotlib, Plotly, Dash, Seaborn

Data Bases: MySQL, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, PostGIS, SQLAlchemy, JuliaDB

docker Containerization: Docker

Graphs: NetworkX, NetworKit, igraph, Gephi, LightGraphs.jl

spark Parallel Computing: Dask, Spark, Moab, TORQUE

Power System Modeling: OpenDSS, CYME, Synergi, DEW

# **OPEN SOURCE MAIN CONTRIBUTIONS**

This section includes some of my contributions to open source softwares and datasets. Find more on my GitHub profile.

#### Libraries

**2021 Nilearn:** Core-developer and maintainer

Nilearn is a python package for fast and easy statistical learning on neuroimaging data.

2019 StreamGraphs.jl: Creator

StreamGraphs.jl is a Julia package to work with stream graphs and link streams.

**2018 DiTTo (Distribution Transformation Tool):** Creator and core-developer 2017 - 2018 DiTTo is a Python package which aims at providing an open source framework to convert various distribution system modeling formats.

#### **Datasets**

**2018 Santa-Fe Synthetic Network:** This dataset is a large-scale synthetic distribution and sub-transmission network for the city of Santa Fe, New-Mexico, USA.

**2017 The Power Grid Dataset:** This is a dataset of topologies of real power grid systems. Developed at Telecom SuParis.

# Community

2021 Nilearn dev-days 2021: Organizer

This online international coding sprint took place March 5th-7th 2021 around Nilearn and Nibabel.

# **TEACHING AND ADVISING**

- **2020** Mentoring Master student M. Olivier Pierre on *Robustness of Web of Trust Mechanisms*. Introduction to the modeling of dynamical systems (UPMC, ARE, L1), coordinator: Nicolas Maudet. 40 hours
- **2019** Introduction to the modeling of dynamical systems (UPMC, ARE, L1), coordinator: Nicolas Maudet. 40 hours
- **2016** Mentoring Master student M. Lester Padilla on *Reconstructing the European Power Grid from OpenstreetMap data*. Apr. 2016 Sept. 2016.
- **2016** Monitorat at UPMC. Programming basics in Python (L1), coordinator: Fabien Tarissan Python programming (M1). 64 hours
- **2015** Monitorat at UPMC. C programming project (L3), coordinator: Xavier Clady, Artificial Intelligence for 2 players games (L2), coordinator: Sylvain Lamprier. 64 hours
- **2014** Monitorat at UPMC. TCP/IP Networking (M1), coordinator: Promethee Spathis, C programming project (L3), coordinator: Xavier Clady. 64 hours

# **PUBLICATIONS**

### **Conferences**

- **2019** Nicolas Gensollen, Matthieu Latapy
  - $Interplay\ between\ social\ and\ financial\ interactions\ in\ a\ crypto-currency,$

Presented at MARAMI 2019 in Dijon, France.

- **2019** Akshay Kumar Jain, Kelsey Horowitz, Fei Ding, Nicolas Gensollen, Barry Mather, and Bryan Palmintier, Quasi-Static Time Series PV Hosting Capacity Methodology and Metrics,
  - Presented at the 2019 IEEE Conference on Innovative Smart Grid Technologies (ISGT) in Washington D.C.
- 2016 Nicolas Gensollen, Vincent Gauthier, Michel Marot, Monique Becker,
  - Submodular Optimization for Control of Prosumer Networks,

Presented at the 2016 IEEE SmartGridComm in Sydney.

- 2015 Nicolas Gensollen, Monique Becker, Vincent Gauthier, Michel Marot,
  - Coalition Formation Algorithm of Prosumers in a Smart Grid Environment,
  - Presented at the 2015 IEEE International Conference on Communications (ICC) in London.

### **Journals**

- **2020** Nicolas Gensollen, Matthieu Latapy
  - Do you trade with your friends or become friends with your trading partners?
  - A case study in the G1 cryptocurrency,
  - Applied Network Science, 2020.
- 2019 Nicolas Gensollen, Kelsey Horowitz, Bryan Palmintier, Fei Ding, and Barry Mather,
  - Beyond Hosting Capacity: Using Shortest Path Methods to Minimize Upgrade Cost Pathways, IEEE Journal of Photovoltaics, vol. 9, issue 4, 2019
- 2018 Nicolas Gensollen, Vincent Gauthier, Michel Marot, Monique Becker,
  - Stability and Performance of Coalitions of Prosumers Through Diversification in the Smart Grid, IEEE Transactions on Smart Grid, vol.9, issue 2, 2018